[Music]
hello everyone this is Frank D Freitas
and welcome to hellotalk the internet's
laser and holography talk show enjoyed
in over 42 countries throughout the
world and now here's this week's show
[Music]
hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to another week of holotalk
my guest this week is Brian Monahan of
international holographic paper located
in Chalfont Pennsylvania International
holographic paper produces a number of
different commercial Holograms and some
of their recent projects that you may
have had an opportunity to see would be
their video boxes for instance at your
local video store they were responsible
for the Star Trek generations Matrix and
Men In Black which actually was a
production run of 27 million
they're also involved with a system that
they developed called iscan which is a
new way of making dot matrix Holograms
through interferometric laser ablation
and Brian Monahan is going to be coming
on and telling us a little bit about
that technique so let's move on to the
show it was recorded on location in
shelf on Pennsylvania and let's hear
what Brian had to say
hello everyone this is Frank D Freitas
and welcome to another week of hollow
talk we're kicking off a brand new
season of hollow talk shows and I'm here
in Chalfont Pennsylvania with Brian
Monahan and Brian Monahan is owner of
international holographic paper and what
I'd like to do at this point is to let
Brian take a minute or two to let you
know what international holographic
papers is all about well
um our company started in 1971 and we
were basically in the paper business
selling commodity papers to Commercial
Printing industry about
1988 took a course in holography with
you down at the Franklin Institute got
hooked on it set up tables in the
basement and uh figured out that there's
got to be some way that we can make a
living in this around 1992 we purchased
our first dot matrix photoresist
hologram machine that would produce up
to 12 by 12 inch Images pixel by pixel
and really took off from there we
basically designed now we design all of
our own custom Holograms
electroform emboss and most of the
material that we now distribute is still
paper based just Holograms that are
embossed in the paper for Mass
replication for anything from cosmetic
packaging video boxes
on beer can labels bottle labels and now
a lot of point-of-purchase displays
we're sitting here in a conference room
where we are completely surrounded by
projects that you have worked on with
your company and I was wondering if you
could take a moment just to look around
the room and maybe pick out a few of the
ones that are perhaps some special
projects that you've worked on well it's
a lot of these things were very
interesting and fun somewhere a hell of
a lot more profitable than others but uh
intricate just real quickly a couple of
them that stand out in the video boxes
we won some awards for the Star Trek
generations video box and the Matrix
Video box there are custom Holograms and
mass-produced in large quantities uh
then simple ones like our Men In Black
video box the Men in Black was 27
million video boxes produced all around
the world uh and it was done with a
simple diffraction grading cross-grading
what we call Rainbow
some of the other ones that are more
intriguing is in the CD-ROM packaging we
have one called Skynet there that was
one of the largest Holograms ever
produced in its time about 14 by 20
inches and it had registered lithography
with it to really make it stand out and
be attractive to the consumers some of
the ones I think we're most proud of
them have fun with would be our latest
series of Pokemon the Pokemon craze uh
really did a lot with holography uh the
cards that we produced for the tops
company the last series was the
introduction of six new Pokemon
characters and it utilized a stereogram
2d 3D background image that had about 25
channels of movement in it in full color
as well as integrated dot matrix
hallography on the Forefront with
integrated holographic white so the
cards were completely finished and
didn't need to be printed on top of when
it was done then some of our latest
developments that we did that were
really a lot of fun were more on
prototyping ends we'd shot a large
Coca-Cola bottle about four feet high a
bottle cap of beer on a Friday afternoon
that we blew up to three by four feet
and the latest one was the Ferrari we
just got finished shooting there's a 40
by 90 inches it required three
holographic Masters on our part and a
very wide embossing machine 90 inches
wide to wrap it but it really stood out
and and it it really made us feel that
we really achieved something being able
to produce such a large image in under
10 hours and very economically and get
the results that we did
it's an incredible piece the equipment
that that was created on as far as the
actual equipment that exposed your photo
resist uh could you tell the listeners a
little bit about that technology
of what you can tell about it anyway
well basically we have three dot matrix
machines conventional dot matrix that
expose photoresist uh pixel by pixel
using a blue laser 442 nanometer
wavelength and it goes through each
pixel and rotates the diffraction
grading pixel by pixel corresponding to
a computer graphic we've developed a new
system on our own it's called iscan
there is a video up on the website of
iscan operating and basically it
produces holographic ratings size of
pixels about a thousand times a second
and instead of exposing it indirectly
into a photoresist that needs chemical
development afterwards this is basically
etching for lack of a better term
directly into a piece of plastic the
holographic Groove structures dot by dot
by dot it's basically called laser
ablation or interferometric laser
ablation
how many people do you employ here
right now there's 12 in our organization
uh eight people here and mainly
uh everybody we've one holographer and
everybody else is in support it requires
a tremendous amount of support in
commercial in the commercial end of the
business to show people to educate them
to show samples and to get them
understanding what they can do with
holography and what they can't and how
cost effective it can be when you put it
on a package it does cost more than
white paper but when it sells three
times as much or you gain market share
it that comes back a hundredfold exactly
if there were students out there who
were listening to this perhaps they're
in high school they've worked on a
holography project they're very
interested in holography
what sort of skill sets do you look for
what are the talents that are needed
what do people need to know if they were
to say for instance all of a sudden you
needed to hire four or more holographers
well that's a very good question in that
in today's Marketplace uh companies are
growing dramatically and there is a lack
of skilled labor throughout the world
holographers go from company to company
they're not born
I think people that are interested in
getting into holography uh are the type
of people number one that love it the
dude in their basement are amazed by it
and that's how I got involved into it
um if you love doing it there's a way to
find a way to make money at doing it
what we would require from people Tech
specifically what I would love to have
is a person who understands
um uh programming uh today's type of
laser systems uh stereographic 3D
pulse portrait a lot of different types
of systems are all computer generated
computer controlled so knowing the the
programming language is very important
and staying up to date on that computer
graphics
probably 75 percent of the commercial
hologram shot nowadays are computer
Graphics three-dimensional renderings uh
flat Photoshop Graphics not many models
being made nowadays for commercial
holography so understanding computer
Graphics is a strong point and then
basis of holography
understanding Optics optoelectronics
mechanical engineering things like that
are all important aspects of of how to
put together a setup how to operate a
laser and and what happens to
polarization and things like that when
you start bouncing off of different
mirrors and different Optics
um I don't know if that if you need to
walk in here and say I have a Physics
degree in this degree and that but a
very good understanding people who
understand uh computer computers
programming graphic arts and um uh
basics of holography with an emphasis
also on on optoelectronics they're the
kind of people that we would hire today
I find it interesting that you also
mentioned graphic skills along with that
because a lot of times when we think
about holography we think of it
basically in terms of physics Optics and
photonics but because the computer
itself has made its way into so many
areas of work today I rarely hear it
mention that computer skills would also
be needed so it was interesting that you
mentioned that as well it is important
and one one respect is
if you're a graphic designer you can be
exceptionally well at it if you're a
holographer you can be exceptionally
good holographer but one necessarily
can't work with the other a designer
doesn't know exactly how to design to
shoot a hologram and a helographer may
not know how to design to begin with so
you really need to have the best of both
skills to be able to design what you
want to get out of the finished hologram
that's also taking into account
different personality types as well
because you have someone who's
interested in physics and holography and
that's a certain personality type of
someone who's interested in science and
technology and then you have someone who
would be designing on one of your
workstations and that's more of a
creative type of personality so I can
see where these careers of the future
and this is definitely one of the
careers of the future where you need
quite a bit of a balance in an
individual when you're looking to employ
someone they need to be not only
creative but technically Savvy as well
do you see the field continuing to grow
very much so the projections that were
done in I believe 1997 estimated the
worldwide commercial industry for
holography at about one billion dollars
um that was reassured at our last
conference in 1999 in Florida at the
hollow pack conference
they do estimate I believe in 2002 or
2003 to for it to double to be a two
billion dollar industry when you're
getting to be that size worldwide uh and
that type of 30 to 35 growth every year
it is something that a lot of people are
paying more attention to
holography has proven itself as a
anti-theft device
holography has proven a self to capture
attention and just have a aesthetic
Beauty to it so uh it is worldwide
accepted and I do also see a lot of
different companies within the industry
spending a large amount of money on
Capital Equipment Capital Investments to
be the leader in the future or to
maintain staying leader in the future so
with all the money going into the
industry and all the feedback from the
consumers who utilize the Holograms I
expect at least for the next five ten
years to see this 30 growth with the
technology changing as fast as it's
changing now too how often do you see it
would be necessary to have one of your
employees that's doing the holography
learn new skills
well the toughest thing about this
business is being the best at it to
survive you need to be the best uh you
need to be new and you need to be unique
the people who do that and spend the
money on R D and development are the
people that will exceed and are the
people that have gained the reputation
as being innovators within the industry
as fast as holography in general or
lasers in general are changing which is
so rapid just from a few years ago
having to you know buy two heanies to
the diodes now the same thing is
happening within the hilography industry
so you really need to be at the
Forefront of it
things that you a Machinery that
normally would last in a printing
industry let's say for 10 20 30 years
can become obsolete in two to three
years within this industry so new
product development and things of the
along that line developing new
techniques uh in holography not only to
increase the efficiency lower the cost
but to create new visual effects is
something that's very very important and
you can say something new is coming out
every year at least
so essentially what you're saying is
that you're the one that's creating the
Innovative changes and it wouldn't be
that you would send someone out to learn
something new you're doing that here
yourself
yeah basically you have to take there's
no school to go to to learn the fastest
newest things in holography so you have
to teach yourself
um you have to come up with ideas you
have to spend the money and you have to
try to execute those ideas
some things that we've tried have really
paid off well our eye scan is
testimonial to that some things we've
we've tried were ridiculous and we spent
a lot of money and got nowhere but if we
didn't try we would have never known I
think a lot of people within the
industry are doing the same thing and
that goes back to the education end of
it you got to be smart enough and
well-rounded enough to be able to
program to be able to understand the
optoelectronics the physics and the
basis of holography knowing that you can
go off onto these tangents and come up
with ideas that may or may not work and
try it but that's the only way to
succeed is is to to be one step ahead of
everybody else and coming out with new
and new products
oh you know I'm an old-timer
and
when I look back successful holographers
were still in the basement and then I
drive up to International holographic
paper today and I see one of the most
beautiful complexes that I've ever seen
with holography anywhere this is
beautiful tell us a little about the
building here a square footage for your
Warehouse in different areas like that
well we came from a 8 000 square foot
broken up facility in Glenside
Pennsylvania we had this purpose built
for us about a year ago to this month as
a matter of fact and we designed it with
expansion in mind
we did a lot of separate special things
for hologography we have a 3D table in
there that you saw set up and that whole
room is free-floating that's on its own
slab it has isolation material around
the slab all the walls are floating off
of the slab on a separate piece little
things like that have really helped in
building this facility
basically we have uh 17 000 square feet
here now about 12 000 feet is production
and warehouse and we're seeing uh we're
running out of room very quickly as we
keep vertically integrating
again with the idea of reducing costs
giving better product and better
services to our clients we're running
out of space we do stock a tremendous
amount of holographic material uh
generic for the worldwide Commercial
Printing industry
and we do see that as you vertically
integrate you can we're going to need
another 10 000 square feet very quickly
especially when you get into some of the
large embossing and mass replicating
equipment the metalization
coding and priming things of that nature
before we close could you tell the
listeners a little bit about your
website and what they would find when
they go there
yeah uh our website is uh www it's ihp
hologram
h-o-l-o-g-r-a-m.com ihp hologram.com
basically uh we have a couple videos up
there explaining on how iscan works
also on how conventional dot matrix
holography works so you can have a
little bit of a comparison between the
old technology and the new and there's a
lot of neat photographs up on the
website showing a lot of our client
projects what we've been doing lately
it's also a e-files electronic
newsletter that we send out on a monthly
basis so if anybody would like to see
what's going on in the realm of
commercial holography they can sign up
and every month we send out something of
new new projects that we're doing that
they can see on their consumer shelves
okay I want to thank you very much for
being on the show and I'd like to let
the whole talk listeners know that there
is a link right on the holotalk page for
the international holographic Paper
website and I encourage you to click on
that go over and see what they're all
about and Brian thank you very much for
coming on the show thank you very much
Frank